<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [

  <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc4862 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4862.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc4191 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4191.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc6973 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6973.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc7217 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7217.xml'>
  <!ENTITY I-D.gont-6man-deprecate-eui64-based-addresses SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.gont-6man-deprecate-eui64-based-addresses.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc8947 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8947.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc8948 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8948.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc7844 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7844.xml'>

]>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<rfc category="info" docName="draft-ietf-madinas-mac-address-randomization-latest"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
      <title abbrev="MAC address randomization">
       MAC address randomization
      </title>

    <!-- AUTHORS -->
    <author fullname="Juan Carlos Zuniga"
            initials="JC."
            surname="Zuniga">
      <organization abbrev="CISCO">
        CISCO
      </organization>
      <address>
	    <postal>
          <street></street>
          <city>Montreal</city>
          <code> QC</code>
          <country>Canada</country>
        </postal>
        <email>juzuniga@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Carlos J. Bernardos"
            initials="CJ."
            surname="Bernardos" role="editor">
      <organization abbrev="UC3M">
        Universidad Carlos III de Madrid
      </organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Av. Universidad, 30</street>
          <city>Leganes, Madrid</city>
          <code>28911</code>
          <country>Spain</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+34 91624 6236</phone>
        <email>cjbc@it.uc3m.es</email>
        <uri>http://www.it.uc3m.es/cjbc/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Amelia Andersdotter"
            initials="A."
            surname="Andersdotter">
      <organization abbrev="Sky UK">
        Sky UK Group, Sky Labs
      </organization>
       <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Chatham Way</street>
          <city>Brentwood</city>
          <code>CM14 4DZ</code>
          <country>UK</country>
        </postal>
        <email>amelia.ietf@andersdotter.cc</email>
       </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2022"/>

    <area>Internet</area>

    <workgroup>MADINAS</workgroup>

    <abstract>

      <t>
Internet privacy has become a major concern over the past few years. Users are
becoming more aware that their online activity leaves a vast digital footprint,
that communications are not always properly secured, and that their location and
actions can be easily tracked. One of the main factors for the location tracking
issue is the wide use of long-lasting identifiers, such as MAC addresses.

      </t>

      <t>
There have been several initiatives at the IETF and the IEEE 802 standards
committees to overcome some of these privacy issues. This document provides an
overview of these activities, with the intention to inform the technical
community about them, and help coordinate between present and future
standardization activities.
      </t>

    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>

<!-- BEGIN Terminology -->
    <section anchor="sec:introduction" title="Introduction">

      <t>
Internet privacy is becoming a huge concern, as more and more mobile devices are
getting directly (e.g., via cellular or Wi-Fi) or indirectly (e.g., via a
smartphone using Bluetooth) connected to the Internet. This ubiquitous
connectivity, together with not very secure protocol stacks and the lack of
proper education about privacy make it very easy to track/monitor the location
of users and/or eavesdrop their physical and online activities. This is due to
many factors, such as the vast digital footprint that users leave on the
Internet, for instance sharing information on social networks, cookies used by
browsers and servers to provide a better navigation experience, connectivity
logs that allow tracking of a user’s Layer-2 (L2/MAC) or Layer-3 (L3) address,
web trackers, etc.; and/or the weak (or even null in some cases) authentication
and encryption mechanisms used to secure communications.
      </t>

      <t>
This privacy concern affects all layers of the protocol stack, from the lower
layers involved in the actual access to the network (e.g., the MAC/Layer-2 and
Layer-3 addresses can be used to obtain the location of a user) to higher layer
protocol identifiers and user applications <xref target="wifi_internet_privacy"
/>. In particular, IEEE 802 MAC addresses have historically been an easy target
for tracking users <xref target="wifi_tracking" />.
      </t>

      <t>
There have been several initiatives at the IETF and the IEEE 802 standards
committees to overcome some of these privacy issues. This document provides an
overview of these activities, with the intention to inform the community and
help coordinate between present and futures standardization activities.
      </t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="sec:terminology" title="Terminology">

<!--
      <t>
The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD",
"SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be
interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119" />.
      </t>
-->

      <t>
The following terms are used in this document:

        <list style="empty">

          <t>MAC: Medium Access Control</t>

        </list>

      </t>

    </section>
<!-- END Terminology -->

<!-- BEGIN Problem statement -->
    <section anchor="sec:background" title="Background">

    <section anchor="sec:mac_usage" title="MAC address usage">

        <t>
Most mobile devices used today are Wi-Fi enabled (i.e. they are equipped with an
IEEE 802.11 wireless local area network interface). Wi-Fi interfaces, as any
other kind of IEEE 802-based network interface, like Ethernet (i.e. IEEE 802.3)
have a Layer-2 address also referred to as MAC address, which can be seen by
anybody who can receive the signal transmitted by the network interface. The
format of these addresses is shown in <xref target="fig:ieee802_mac_address_format" />.
        </t>

<figure anchor="fig:ieee802_mac_address_format" title="IEEE 802 MAC Address Format" >
<artwork><![CDATA[
        +--------+--------+---------+--------+--------+---------+
        |  Organizationally Unique  |     Network Interface     |
        |     Identifier (OUI)      | Controller (NIC) Specific |
        +--------+--------+---------+--------+--------+---------+
       /          \
      /            \
     /              \          b0 (U/L bit):
    /                \             0: unicast
   /                  \            1: multicast
  /                    \
 /                      \      b1:
+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+          0: globally unique (OUI enforced)
|b7|b6|b5|b4|b3|b2|b1|b0|          1: locally administered
+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+
]]></artwork>
</figure>

        <t>
MAC addresses can either be universally administered or locally administered.
Universally administered and locally administered addresses are distinguished by
setting the second-least-significant bit of the most significant byte of the
address (the U/L bit).
        </t>

        <t>
A universally administered address is uniquely assigned to a device by its
manufacturer. Most physical devices are provided with a universally administered
address, which is composed of two parts: (i) the Organizationally Unique
Identifier (OUI), which are the first three octets in transmission order and
identify the organization that issued the identifier, and (ii) Network Interface
Controller (NIC) Specific, which are the following three octets, assigned by the
organization that manufactured the NIC, in such a way that the resulting MAC
address is globally unique.
        </t>

        <t>
Locally administered addresses override the burned-in address, and they can
either be set-up by the network administrator, or by the Operating System (OS)
of the device to which the address pertains. However, as explained in further
sections of this document, there are new initiatives at the IEEE 802 and other
organizations to specify ways in which these locally administered addresses
should be assigned, depending on the use case.
        </t>

    </section>
<!-- END Problem statement -->

<!-- BEGIN MAC address randomization -->
    <section anchor="sec:mac_addr_random" title="MAC address randomization">

      <t>
Since universally administered MAC addresses are by definition globally-unique,
when a device uses this MAC address to transmit data -especially over the air-
it is relatively easy to track this device by simple medium observation. Since a
device is usually directly associated to an individual, this poses a privacy
concern <xref target="link_layer_privacy"/>.
      </t>

      <t>
MAC addresses can be easily observed by a third party, such as a passive device
listening to communications in the same network. In an 802.11 network, a station
exposes its MAC address in two different situations:
      </t>

<t><list style="symbols">
	  <t>
While actively scanning for available networks, the MAC address is used in the
Probe Request frames sent by the device (aka IEEE 802.11 STA).
      </t>

	  <t>
Once associated to a given Access Point (AP), the MAC address is used in frame
transmission and reception, as one of the addresses used in the address fields
of an IEEE 802.11 frame.
      </t>
</list></t>

	  <t>
One way to overcome this privacy concern is by using randomly generated MAC
addresses. As described in the previous section, the IEEE 802 addressing
includes one bit to specify if the hardware address is locally or globally
administered. This allows generating local addresses without the need of any
global coordination mechanism to ensure that the generated address is still
unique within the local network. This feature can be used to generate random
addresses, which decouple the globally-unique identifier from the device and
therefore make it more difficult to track a user device from its MAC/L2 address
<xref target="enhancing_location_privacy" />.
      </t>

    </section>





    <section anchor="sec:mac_addr_experiments" title="Privacy Workshop, Tutorial and Experiments at IETF and IEEE 802 meetings">

	<t>
As an outcome to the STRINT W3C/IAB Workshop <xref target="strint" />, on July
2014 a Tutorial on Pervasive Surveillance of the Internet - Designing Privacy
into Internet Protocols was given at the IEEE 802 Plenary meeting in San Diego
<xref target="privacy_tutorial" />. The Tutorial provided an update on the
recent developments regarding Internet privacy, the actions that other SDOs such
as IETF were taking, and guidelines that were being followed when developing new
Internet protocol specifications (e.g. <xref target="RFC6973" />). The Tutorial
highlighted some Privacy concerns applicable specifically to Link Layer
technologies and provided suggestions on how IEEE 802 could help addressing
them.
	</t>

	<t>
Following the discussions and interest within the IEEE 802 community, on 18 July
2014 the IEEE 802 Executive Committee (EC) created an IEEE 802 EC Privacy
Recommendation Study Group (SG) <xref target="ieee_privacy_ecsg" />. The work
and discussions from the group have generated multiple outcomes, such as: 802E
PAR: Recommended Practice for Privacy Considerations for IEEE 802 Technologies
<xref target="IEEE_802E" />, and the 802c PAR: Standard for Local and
Metropolitan Area Networks - Overview and Architecture Amendment - Local Medium
Access Control (MAC) Address Usage <xref target="IEEE_802c" />.
	</t>

	<t>
In order to test the effects of MAC address randomization, major trials were
conducted at the IETF and IEEE 802 meetings between November 2014 and March 2015
- IETF91, IETF92 and IEEE 802 Plenary in Berlin. The purpose of the experiments
was to evaluate the use of MAC address randomization from two different
perspectives: (i) the effect on the connectivity experience of the end-user,
also checking if applications and operating systems (OSs) were affected; and
(ii) the potential impact on the network infrastructure itself. Some of the
findings were published in <xref target="wifi_internet_privacy" />.
      </t>

      <t>
During the experiments it was observed that the probability of address
duplication in a network with this characteristics is negligible. The
experiments also showed that other protocol identifiers can be correlated and
therefore be used to still track an individual. Hence, effective privacy tools
should not work in isolation at a single layer, but they should be coordinated
with other privacy features at higher layers.
      </t>

      <t>
Since then, MAC randomization has further been implemented by mobile operating
systems to provide better privacy for mobile phone users when connecting to
public wireless networks <xref target="privacy_ios" />, <xref
target="privacy_windows" />, <xref target="privacy_android" />.
	  </t>


    </section>
<!-- END L2 address randomization -->

    </section>

<!-- BEGIN Tools -->
    <section anchor="sec:mac_rnd_at_ieee802" title="Recent RCM activities at the IEEE 802">

      <t>
Practical experiences of Randomized And Changing MAC Addresses (RCM) in live
devices helped researchers fine-tune their understanding of attacks against
randomization mechanisms <xref target="when_mac_randomization_fails" />. At IEEE
802.11 these research experiences eventually formed the basis for a specified
mechanism introduced in the IEEE 802.11aq in 2018 which randomize MAC addresses
that recommends mechanisms to avoid pitfalls <xref target="IEEE_802_11_aq" />.
      </t>

      <t>
More recent developments include turning on MAC randomization in mobile
operating systems by default, which has an impact on the ability of network
operators to personalize or customize services <xref
target="rcm_user_experience_csd" />. Therefore, follow-on work in the IEEE
802.11 mapped effects of potentially large uptake of randomized MAC identifiers
on a number of commonly offered operator services in 2019<xref
target="rcm_tig_final_report" />. In the summer of 2020 this work emanated in
two new standards projects with the purpose of developing mechanisms that do not
decrease user privacy and enable an optimal user experience when the MAC address
of a device in an Extended Service Set is randomized or changes <xref
target="rcm_user_experience_par" /> and user privacy solutions applicable to
IEEE Std 802.11 <xref target="rcm_privacy_par" />.
      </t>

      <t>
The IEEE 802.1 working group has also published a specification that defines a
local MAC address space structure, known as the Structured Local Address Plan
(SLAP). This structure designates a range of local MAC addresses for protocols
using a Company ID (CID) assigned by the IEEE Registration Authority. Another
range of local MAC addresses is designated for assignment by administrators. The
specification recommends a range of local MAC addresses for use by IEEE 802
protocols <xref target="IEEE_802c" />.
	  </t>

      <t>
Work within the IEEE 802.1 Security task group on privacy recommendations for
all IEEE 802 network technologies has also looked into general recommendations
on identifiers, reaching the conclusion that temporary and transient identifiers
are preferably in network technology design if there are no compelling reasons
of service quality for a newly introduced identifier to be permanent. This work
has been specified in the recently published IEEE P802E: Recommended Practice
for Privacy Considerations for IEEE 802 Technologies <xref target="IEEE_802E"
/>. The IEEE P802E specification will form part of the basis for the review of
user privacy solutions applicable to IEEE Std 802.11 (aka Wi-Fi) devices as part
of the RCM <xref target="rcm_privacy_csd" /> efforts.
</t>

<t>
Currently, two task groups in IEEE 802.11 are dealing with issues related to RCM:

  <list style="symbols">

    <t>
The IEEE 802.11bh task group, looking at mitigating the repercussions that RCM
creates on 802.11 networks and related services, and
    </t>

    <t>
The IEEE 802.11bi task group, which will define modifications to the IEEE Std
802.11 medium access control (MAC) specification to specify new mechanisms that
address and improve user privacy.
    </t>

  </list>

</t>

    </section>
<!-- END Tools -->

    <section anchor="sec:wba" title="Recent MAC randomization-related activities at the WBA">

      <t>
At the Wireless Broadband Alliance (WBA), the Testing and Interoperability Work
Group has been looking at the issues related to MAC address randomization and
has identified a list of potential impacts of these changes to existing systems
and solutions, mainly related to Wi-Fi identification.
      </t>

      <t>
As part of this work, WBA has documented a set of use cases that a Wi-Fi
Identification Standard should address in order to scale and achieve longer term
sustainability of deployed services. A first version of this document has been
liaised with the IETF as part of the MAC Address Device Identification for
Network and Application Services (MADINAS) activities through the "Wi-Fi
Identification In a post MAC Randomization Era v1.0" paper <xref
target="wba_paper" />.
      </t>

    </section>

<!-- BEGIN Evaluation -->
    <section anchor="sec:mac_rnd_at_ietf" title="MAC randomization-related activities at the IETF">

      <t>
Several IP address assignment mechanisms such as the IPv6 stateless
autoconfiguration techniques (SLAAC) <xref target="RFC4862" /> generate the
Interface Identifier (IID) of the address from its MAC address (via EUI64),
which then becomes visible to all IPv6 communication peers. This potentially
allows for global tracking of a device at L3 from any point on the Internet.
Besides, the prefix part of the address provides meaningful insights of the
physical location of the device in general, which together with the MAC
address-based IID, makes it easier to perform global device tracking.
      </t>

      <t>
There are some solutions that might mitigate this privacy threat, such as the
use of temporary addresses <xref target="RFC4191" />, the use of opaque IIDs
<xref target="RFC7217" />, <xref
target="I-D.gont-6man-deprecate-eui64-based-addresses" />. Next, we briefly
describe how these solutions work.
      </t>

      <t>
<xref target="RFC4191" /> identifies and describes the privacy issues associated
with embedding MAC stable addressing information into the IPv6 addresses (as
part of the IID) and describes some mechanisms to mitigate the associated
problems. The specification is meant for IPv6 nodes that auto-configure IPv6
addresses based on the MAC address (EUI-64 mechanism). It defines how to create
additional addresses (generally known as "temporary addresses") based on a
random interface identifier for the purpose of initiating outgoing sessions.
These "random" or temporary addresses are meant to be used for a short period of
time (hours to days) and would then be deprecated. Deprecated addresses can
continue to be used for already established connections, but are not used to
initiate new connections. New temporary addresses are generated periodically to
replace temporary addresses that expire. In order to do so, a node produces a
sequence of temporary global scope addresses from a sequence of interface
identifiers that appear to be random in the sense that it is difficult for an
outside observer to predict a future address (or identifier) based on a current
one, and it is difficult to determine previous addresses (or identifiers)
knowing only the present one. The main problem with the temporary addresses is
that they should not be used by applications that listen for incoming
connections (as these are supposed to be waiting on permanent/well-known
identifiers). Besides, if a node changes network and comes back to a previously
visited one, the temporary addresses that the node would use will be different,
and this might be an issue in certain networks where addresses are used for
operational purposes (e.g., filtering or authentication). <xref target="RFC7217"
/>, summarized next, partially addresses the problems aforementioned.
      </t>

      <t>
<xref target="RFC7217"/> defines a method for generating IPv6 IIDs to be used
with IPv6 Stateless Address Autoconfiguration (SLAAC), such that an IPv6 address
configured using this method is stable within each subnet, but the corresponding
IID changes when the host moves from one network to another. This method is
meant to be an alternative to generating Interface Identifiers based on MAC
addresses, such that the benefits of stable addresses can be achieved without
sacrificing the security and privacy of users. The method defined to generate
the IPv6 IID is based on computing a hash function which takes as input
information that is stable and associated to the interface (e.g., MAC address or
local interface identifier), stable information associated to the visited
network (e.g., IEEE 802.11 SSID), the IPv6 prefix, and a secret key, plus some
other additional information. This basically ensures that a different IID is
generated when any of the input fields changes (such as the network or the
prefix), but that the IID is the same within each subnet.
      </t>

      <t>
In addition to the former documents, <xref target="RFC8947" />
proposes an extension to DHCPv6 that allows a scalable approach to link-layer
address assignments where preassigned link-layer address assignments (such as by
a manufacturer) are not possible or unnecessary. <xref
target="RFC8948" /> proposes extensions to DHCPv6 protocols
to enable a DHCPv6 client or a DHCPv6 relay to indicate a preferred SLAP
quadrant to the server, so that the server may allocate MAC addresses in the
quadrant requested by the relay or client.
      </t>

      <t>
Not only MAC and IP addresses can be used for tracking purposes. Some DHCP
options carry unique identifiers. These identifiers can enable device tracking
even if the device administrator takes care of randomizing other potential
identifications like link-layer addresses or IPv6 addresses. <xref
target="RFC7844" /> introduces anonymity profiles, designed for clients that
wish to remain anonymous to the visited network. The profiles provide guidelines
on the composition of DHCP or DHCPv6 messages, designed to minimize disclosure
of identifying information. <xref target="RFC7844" /> also indicates that the
link-layer address, IP address, and DHCP identifier shall evolve in synchrony.
      </t>

<!--
      <t>
Lately, the MAC Address Device Identification for Network and Application Services (MADINAS) IETF BoF
has discussed the need to examine the effect of RCM schemes on network and application services in several
scenarios identified as relevant.
      </t>
-->

    </section>
<!-- END Evaluation -->

<!-- BEGIN OSes current practices -->
      <section anchor="sec:os_current_practices" title="OS current practices">

        <t>
Since this content can evolve with time, it is now hosted at https://github.com/ietf-wg-madinas/draft-ietf-madinas-mac-address-randomization/blob/main/OS-current-practices.md
        </t>

      </section>
<!-- END OSes current practices -->

    <section anchor="rcm-types" title="A taxonomy of MAC address selection
                                       policies">
      <t>
        This section documents five different policies for MAC address selection.
      </t>

      <t>
        XXX-The names are subject to change.
        The "M" in MAC is included in the acronym, but not the "A" from address.
        This allows one to talk about a PVOM Address, or PNGM Address.
      </t>

      <t>
        The names are all in the form for per-period-of-time-selection.
      </t>
      <section anchor="policy-pvom" title="Per-Vendor OUI MAC address (PVOM)">

        <t>
          This form of MAC address selection is the historical default.
        </t>
        <t>
          The vendor obtains an Organizationally Unique Identifier (OUI) from the IEEE.
          This has been a 24-bit prefix (including two upper bits which are
          set specifically) that is assigned to the vendor.
          The vendor generates a unique 24-bit value for the lower 24-bits,
          forming the 48-bit MAC address.
          It has not been unusual for the 24-bit value to be taken as an
          incrementing counter, assigned at the factory, and burnt into
          non-volatile storage.
        </t>

        <t>
          Note that 802.15.4 use 64-bit MAC addresses, and the IEEE assigns
          32-bit prefixes.
          The IEEE has indicated that there may be a future Ethernet
          specification using 64-bit MAC addresses.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="policy-pdgm" title="Per-Device Generated MAC address (PDGM)">

        <t>
          This form of MAC address is randomly generated by the device, usually upon first boot.
          The resulting MAC address is stored in non-volatile storage and is
          used for the rest of the device lifetime.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="policy-pbgm" title="Per-Boot Generated MAC address (PBGM)">

        <t>
          This form of MAC address is randomly generated by the device, each
          time the device is booted.

          The resulting MAC address is *not* stored in non-volatile storage.
          It does not persist across power cycles.

          This case may sometimes be a PDGM where the non-volatile storage is no longer functional
          (or has failed).
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="policy-pngm" title="Per-Network Generated MAC adress (PNGM)">

        <t>
          This form of MAC address is generated each time a new network
          connection is created.
        </t>
        <t>
          This is typically used with WiFi (802.11) networks where the network is identified by an SSID Name.
          The generated address is stored on non-volatile storage, indexed by the SSID.
          Each time the device returns to a network with the same SSID, the
          device uses the saved MAC address.
        </t>

        <t>
          It is possible to use PNGM for wired ethernet connections through
          some passive observation of network traffic, such as STP, LLDP,
          DHCP or Router Advertisements to determine which network has been
          attached.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="policy-ppgm" title="Per-Period Generated MAC address (PPGM)">

        <t>
          This form of MAC address is generated periodically.
          Typical numbers are around every twelve hours.
          Like PNGM, it is used primarily with WiFi (802.11).
        </t>

        <t>
          When the MAC address changes, the station disconnects from the current
          session and reconnects using the new MAC address.
          This will involve a new WPA/802.1x session: new EAP, TLS, etc. negotiations.
          A new DHCP, Router-Advertisement will be done.
          TBD: it is unclear if any TLS session-resumption ticket (used by
          EAP-TLS) can or should be retained across a change of the MAC address.
        </t>
        <t>
          If DHCP is used, then a new DUID is generated so as to not link to
          the previous connection, and the result is usually new IP addresses
          allocated.
        </t>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">

      <t>
N/A.
      </t>

    </section>


    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">

      <t>
TBD.
      </t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgments" title="Acknowledgments">

      <t>
Authors would like to thank Guillermo Sanchez Illan for the extensive tests
performed on different OSes to analyze their behavior regarding address
randomization.
      </t>

      <t>
Authors would like to thank Jerome Henry and Hai Shalom for their review and
comments on previous versions of this document. Authors would also like to thank
Michael Richardson for his contibutions on the taxonomy section.
      </t>

    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title="Normative References">
      &rfc2119;
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">

      &rfc4862;
      &rfc4191;
      &rfc6973;
      &rfc7217;
      &I-D.gont-6man-deprecate-eui64-based-addresses;
      &rfc8947;
      &rfc8948;
      &rfc7844;

      <reference anchor="wifi_internet_privacy" >
        <front>
          <title>Wi-Fi Internet Connectivity and Privacy: Hiding your tracks on the wireless Internet</title>
          <author initials="CJ." surname="Bernardos" fullname="Carlos J. Bernardos">
          </author>
          <author initials="JC." surname="Zúñiga" fullname="Juan C. Zúñiga">
          </author>
          <author initials="P." surname="O'Hanlon" fullname="Piers O'Hanlon">
          </author>
          <date month="October" year="2015"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Standards for Communications and Networking (CSCN), 2015 IEEE Conference on" value="" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="link_layer_privacy" >
        <front>
          <title>Privacy at the link layer</title>
           <author initials="P." surname="O'Hanlon" fullname="Piers O'Hanlon">
          </author>
		  <author initials="J." surname="Wright" fullname="J. Wright">
          </author>
          <author initials="I." surname="Brown" fullname="Ian Brown">
          </author>
          <date month="February" year="2014"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Contribution at W3C/IAB workshop on Strengthening the Internet Against Pervasive Monitoring (STRINT)" value="" />
      </reference>


      <reference anchor="enhancing_location_privacy" >
        <front>
          <title>Enhancing location privacy in wireless LAN through disposable interface identifiers: a quantitative analysis</title>
           <author initials="M." surname="Gruteser" fullname="M. Gruteser">
          </author>
		  <author initials="D." surname="Grunwald" fullname="D. Grunwald">
          </author>
          <date month="" year="2005"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Mobile Networks and Applications, vol. 10, no. 3, pp. 315–325" value="" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="privacy_ios" target="https://support.apple.com/en-us/HT211227">
  	<front>
    		<title>Use private Wi-Fi addresses in iOS 14, iPadOS 14, and watchOS 7</title>
    		<author initials="" surname="Apple" fullname="Apple">
      			<organization></organization>
    		</author>
    		<date />
  	</front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="strint" target="https://www.w3.org/2014/strint/">
  	<front>
    		<title>A W3C/IAB workshop on Strengthening the Internet Against Pervasive Monitoring (STRINT)</title>
    		<author initials="" surname="W3C/IAB" fullname="W3C/IAB">
      			<organization></organization>
    		</author>
    		<date />
  	</front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="ieee_privacy_ecsg" target="http://www.ieee802.org/PrivRecsg/">
  	<front>
    		<title>IEEE 802 EC Privacy Recommendation Study Group</title>
    		<author initials="" surname="IEEE 802 Privacy EC SG" fullname="IEEE 802 Privacy EC SG">
      			<organization></organization>
    		</author>
    		<date />
  	</front>
      </reference>


      <reference anchor="privacy_tutorial" target="https://mentor.ieee.org/802-ec/dcn/14/ec-14-0043-01-00EC-internet-privacy-tutorial.pdf">
  	<front>
    		<title>Tutorial on Pervasive Surveillance of the Internet - Designing Privacy into Internet Protocols </title>
           <author initials="A." surname="Cooper" fullname="Alissa Cooper">
          </author>
		  <author initials="T." surname="Hardie" fullname="Ted Hardie">
          </author>
  		  <author initials="JC." surname="Zuniga" fullname="Juan-Carlos Zuniga">
          </author>
		  <author initials="L." surname="Chen" fullname="Lily Chen">
		  </author>
		  <author initials="P." surname="O'Hanlon" fullname="Piers O'Hanlon">
          </author>

    		<date />
  	</front>
      </reference>


      <reference anchor="wifi_tracking" target="https://www.independent.co.uk/life-style/gadgets-and-tech/news/updated-london-s-bins-are-tracking-your-smartphone-8754924.html">
  	<front>
    		<title>London's bins are tracking your smartphone</title>
    		<author initials="" surname="The Independent" fullname="The Independent">
      			<organization></organization>
    		</author>
    		<date />
  	</front>
      </reference>



      <reference anchor="privacy_android" target="https://source.android.com/devices/tech/connect/wifi-mac-randomization-behavior">
  	<front>
    		<title>MAC Randomization Behavior</title>
    		<author initials="" surname="Android
Open Source Project" fullname="Android
Open Source Project">
      			<organization></organization>
    		</author>
    		<date />
  	</front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="privacy_windows" target="https://support.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/how-to-use-random-hardware-addresses-ac58de34-35fc-31ff-c650-823fc48eb1bc">
  	<front>
    		<title>Windows: How to use random hardware addresses</title>
    		<author initials="" surname="Microsoft" fullname="Microsoft">
      			<organization></organization>
    		</author>
    		<date />
  	</front>
      </reference>



      <reference anchor="when_mac_randomization_fails" >
        <front>
          <title>A Study of MAC Address Randomization in Mobile Devices and When it Fails</title>
           <author initials="J." surname="Martin" fullname="J. Martin">
           </author>
	   <author initials="T." surname="Mayberry" fullname="T. Mayberry">
           </author>
	   <author initials="C." surname="Donahue" fullname="C. Donahue">
           </author>
	   <author initials="L." surname="Foppe" fullname="L. Foppe">
           </author>
	   <author initials="L." surname="Brown" fullname="L. Brown">
           </author>
	   <author initials="C." surname="Riggins" fullname="C. Riggins">
           </author>
	   <author initials="E.C." surname="Rye" fullname="E.C. Rye">
           </author>
	   <author initials="D." surname="Brown" fullname="D. Brown">
           </author>
          <date month="" year="2017"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="arXiv:1703.02874v2 [cs.CR]" value="" />
	    </reference>


	    <reference anchor="IEEE_802E" >
              <front>
          <title>IEEE 802E-2020 - IEEE Recommended Practice for Privacy Considerations for IEEE 802 Technologies</title>
	  <author fullname="802.1 WG - 802 LAN/MAN architecture">
          </author>
          <date month="" year="2020"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="IEEE 802E" value="" />
	    </reference>

	    <reference anchor="IEEE_802c" >
              <front>
          <title>IEEE 802c-2017 - IEEE Standard for Local and Metropolitan Area Networks:Overview and Architecture--Amendment 2: Local Medium Access Control (MAC) Address Usage</title>
	  <author fullname="802.1 WG - 802 LAN/MAN architecture">
          </author>
          <date month="" year="2017"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="IEEE 802c" value="" />
	    </reference>

	    <reference anchor="IEEE_802_11_aq" >
              <front>
          <title>IEEE 802.11aq-2018 - IEEE Standard for Information technology--Telecommunications and information exchange between systems Local and metropolitan area networks--Specific requirements Part 11: Wireless LAN Medium Access Control (MAC) and Physical Layer (PHY) Specifications Amendment 5: Preassociation Discovery</title>
	  <author fullname="802.11 WG - Wireless LAN Working Group">
          </author>
          <date month="" year="2018"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="IEEE 802.11" value="" />
	    </reference>

	    <reference anchor="rcm_user_experience_csd" >
        <front>
          <title>IEEE 802.11 Randomized And Changing MAC Addresses Study Group CSD on user experience mechanisms</title>
           <author fullname="802.11 WG RCM SG">
          </author>
          <date month="" year="2020"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="doc.:IEEE 802.11-20/1117r3" value="" />
	    </reference>

	    <reference anchor="rcm_tig_final_report" >
        <front>
          <title>IEEE 802.11 Randomized And Changing MAC Addresses Topic Interest Group Report</title>
           <author fullname="802.11 WG RCM TIG">
          </author>
          <date month="" year="2019"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="doc.:IEEE 802.11-19/1442r9" value="" />
	    </reference>

	    <reference anchor="rcm_user_experience_par" >
        <front>
          <title>IEEE 802.11 Randomized And Changing MAC Addresses Study Group PAR on user experience mechanisms</title>
           <author fullname="802.11 WG RCM SG">
          </author>
          <date month="" year="2020"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="doc.:IEEE 802.11-20/742r5" value="" />
	    </reference>

	    <reference anchor="rcm_privacy_par" >
        <front>
          <title>IEEE 802.11 Randomized And Changing MAC Addresses Study Group PAR on privacy mechanisms</title>
           <author fullname="802.11 WG RCM SG">
          </author>
          <date month="" year="2020"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="doc.:IEEE 802.11-19/854r7" value="" />
	    </reference>

	    <reference anchor="rcm_privacy_csd" >
        <front>
          <title>IEEE 802.11 Randomized And Changing MAC Addresses Study Group CSD on user experience mechanisms</title>
           <author fullname="802.11 WG RCM SG">
          </author>
          <date month="" year="2020"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="doc.:IEEE 802.11-20/1346r1" value="" />
	    </reference>

	    <reference anchor="wba_paper" >
        <front>
          <title>Wi-Fi Identification Scope for Liasing - In a post MAC Randomization Era</title>
           <author fullname="Wireless Broadband Alliance">
          </author>
          <date month="March" year="2020"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="doc.:WBA Wi-Fi ID Intro: Post MAC Randomization Era v1.0 - IETF liaison" value="" />
	    </reference>



    </references>

  </back>

</rfc>

